<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R | Samuel Langton</title>
    <link>/tag/r/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>R</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu347c2c227070d4d829f6f2e71f22c263_2514_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>R</title>
      <link>/tag/r/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update: lockdown crime trends</title>
      <link>/post/update_lockdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/update_lockdown/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=4.9&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few weeks I have spent a bit of time exploring police recorded crime trends before and after the UK-wide lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been talk of lockdowns representing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12103-020-09546-0&#34;&gt;largest criminological experiment in history&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, determining the impact of this ‘experiment’ using police recorded crime data is not straightforward. Lots of parameters will have changed beyond people’s routine activities, amongst them, people’s ability and willingness to report crimes to the police, and policing resource allocation. It might be some time before we can fully understand how lockdowns have curbed the spatial and temporal patterns of crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.police.uk/&#34;&gt;open&lt;/a&gt; police recorded crime data can offer insight into how criminal behaviour might have changed in the past few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;visualising-trends&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Visualising trends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/lockdown-crime-trends-why-antisocial-behaviour-is-up-140479&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; of mine explored how crime trends changed in March and April following the lockdown using London as a case study. It used a descriptive visualisation which was inspired by those used in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/a26fbf7e-48f8-11ea-aeb3-955839e06441&#34;&gt;the FT&lt;/a&gt; to track coronavirus deaths whilst accounting for seasonal changes in death rates. A key characteristic of long-term crime trends is seasonality. To disentangle fluctuations in crime, and try to pinpoint irregularity resulting from lockdown measures, we must account for typical monthly fluctuations. Even then, monthly data is &lt;a href=&#34;https://the-sra.org.uk/SRA/Blog/whyyoucantidentifychangesincrimebycomparingthismonthtolastmonth.aspx&#34;&gt;far from ideal&lt;/a&gt;, but you can’t have everything (especially when working from your living room).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have some updated data – up to and including May, when some lockdown rules were relaxed – which demonstrates the start of a turnaround in crime trends. The code to make this visual is now available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/crime_covid_visual&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/full_met.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dramatic declines in burglary, robbery, theft and shoplifting observed in March and April have begun to reverse, or at least stabilise. Bicycle theft has more or less returned to normal when compared with previous years. As lockdown restrictions have eased, opportunities for crime have begun to (re)emerge. Counts are still unusually low amongst many crime types, but we are certainly witnessing a turnaround.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that we can attribute most ASB incidents to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-52298016&#34;&gt;lockdown breaches&lt;/a&gt;, it is no surprise to see counts beginning to decline. It will be interesting to see where this goes in June and July. We might see a resurgence of ‘traditional’ ASB amidst a fall in incidents associated with lockdown breaches, which will complicate the picture somewhat. We will be able to disentangle this through the analysis of secure records which provide some context to incidents (e.g. text logs), but the continued closure of universities (and thus, many secure data facilities) might slow this down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;drug-activity&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Drug activity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most interesting talking points is around drugs. Initially, some reports suggested that drug use would &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/may/03/coronavirus-crisis-could-increase-users-drug-habits-report&#34;&gt;rise&lt;/a&gt; during lockdown, partly due to the resultant strains on mental health. Now, there are reports that usage, at least for party drugs like ecstasy and cocaine, has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/jun/29/fall-in-use-of-party-drugs-as-more-britons-turn-to-alcohol-in-lockdown&#34;&gt;declined&lt;/a&gt;. We might then have expected a fall in drug offences, which includes possession, consumption and/or supply. Instead, we’ve seen an unprecedented increase throughout April and May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is perfectly plausible that drug activity, such as those relating to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalcrimeagency.gov.uk/what-we-do/crime-threats/drug-trafficking/county-lines&#34;&gt;‘County Lines’&lt;/a&gt;, has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2020/apr/13/gangs-still-forcing-children-into-county-lines-drug-trafficking-police-covid-19-lockdown&#34;&gt;not changed much&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://shoc.rusi.org/informer/part-2-how-covid-19-affecting-county-lines&#34;&gt;declined&lt;/a&gt;, even amidst an increase in the number of offences being recorded by the police. Some forces reported an increase in arrests simply due to dealers &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-52344249&#34;&gt;sticking out&lt;/a&gt; on empty streets. This has been described as like &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/gmhales/status/1249962083631980549&#34;&gt;shooting fish in a barrel&lt;/a&gt; for police, and represents a good example of how trends in police recorded crime – however useful – should be interpreted carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The monthly release of open police crime data in the UK offers a useful on-the-fly opportunity to examine how the lockdown may have impacted on crime. I’ll be updating this visual periodically upon new data releases to see how things are changing. Please do &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.samlangton.info/#contact&#34;&gt;get in contact&lt;/a&gt; if you have any suggestions or comments so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;further-reads&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further reads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stickle, B., &amp;amp; Felson, M. (2020). Crime Rates in a Pandemic: the Largest Criminological Experiment in History. American Journal of Criminal Justice, 1-12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashby, M. (2020). Changes in police calls for service during the early months of the 2020 coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gerell, M. (2020). Minor covid-19 association with crime in Sweden, a five week follow up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R</title>
      <link>/project/r-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/r-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have taught a number of courses using R and RStudio, including the development of teaching material both on my own and with colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-visualisation-in-r-using-crime-data&#34;&gt;Data visualisation in R using crime data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-day workshop on visualisation and mapping at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cmi.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cathie Marsh Institute&lt;/a&gt; (University of Manchester) in collaboration with the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Data Service&lt;/a&gt;. Material is available on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/data_viz_R_workshop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/news-and-events/eventsitem/?id=5552&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Data Service website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;r-for-police-forces&#34;&gt;R for police forces&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-day workshop on data wrangling and visualisation for West Midlands Police Force. Please get in contact for material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;r-for-criminologists&#34;&gt;R for criminologists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-day workshop on data wrangling, visualisation and mapping hosted at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.esc-eurocrim.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;European Society of Criminology&lt;/a&gt; with colleagues from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.space-place-crime.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Space Place and Crime working group&lt;/a&gt;. Material is available on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/ESC2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rpubs.com/spaceplacecrime&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rpubs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-started-in-r---an-introduction-to-data-analysis-and-visualisation&#34;&gt;Getting Started in R - an introduction to data analysis and visualisation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4-day comprehensive introductory course at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.methods.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Methods@Manchester&lt;/a&gt; summer school, co-taught with colleagues. Material is available as a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rcatlord.github.io/GSinR/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cluster-analysis-in-r&#34;&gt;Cluster analysis in R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-day workshop introducing cluster analysis in R at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cmi.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cathie Marsh Institute&lt;/a&gt; (University of Manchester), co-taught with a colleage. Please get in contact for material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;r-for-social-scientists&#34;&gt;R for social scientists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a qualified instructor for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://carpentries.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Data and Software Carpentries&lt;/a&gt;, and supported colleagues in teaching the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://datacarpentry.org/r-socialsci/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;social science workshop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Akmedoids. Anchored kmedoids for longitudinal data clustering</title>
      <link>/publication/akmedoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/akmedoid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
