<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Samuel Langton</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Samuel Langton</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu347c2c227070d4d829f6f2e71f22c263_2514_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Samuel Langton</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small area variation in crime effects of COVID-19 policies in England and Wales</title>
      <link>/publication/covid_smallarea_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/covid_smallarea_preprint/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The accuracy of crime statistics. Assessing the impact of police data bias on geographic crime analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/crimsim_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/crimsim_preprint/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Six Months In. Pandemic Crime Trends in England and Wales</title>
      <link>/publication/covid_crimescience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/covid_crimescience/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anchored k-medoids. A novel adaptation of k-medoids further refined to measure long-term instability in the exposure to crime</title>
      <link>/publication/akmedoid_jcss/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/akmedoid_jcss/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policing and mental ill-health. Using big data to assess the scale and severity of, and the frontline resources committed to, mental ill-health related calls-for-service</title>
      <link>/publication/pmih_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/pmih_preprint/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The universality of street segments: length and sinuosity</title>
      <link>/post/street_segments_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/street_segments_1/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In recent years, a consensus has begun to emerge over the suitability of street segments for visualising and analysing the geographic patterning of crime. A number of studies have argued / demonstrated that these so-called ‘micro’ places are not only &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;id=ROZoAgAAQBAJ&amp;amp;oi=fnd&amp;amp;pg=PP1&amp;amp;dq=weisburd+street+segments&amp;amp;ots=OkrI6wjGXS&amp;amp;sig=nDXmxB3UAgNe4e5kDa4oa2-RGII&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=weisburd%20street%20segments&amp;amp;f=false&#34;&gt;theoretically meaningful&lt;/a&gt; behavioural spaces, but that &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10940-015-9276-3&#34;&gt;most action&lt;/a&gt; occurs among street segments. This makes them particularly useful units of analysis for studying criminal behaviour and designing crime-reducing interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how useful is the ‘street segment’ in different urban contexts? To what extent are these micro units comparable between cities, and between countries? So far, I haven’t found much data-driven research into the uniformity and ‘universality’ of street segments in terms of their physical characteristics. But to me, there are reasons to examine this issue further. In Sweden, for instance, street segments have been described as &lt;a href=&#34;https://search.proquest.com/docview/1899605599?fromopenview=true&amp;amp;pq-origsite=gscholar&#34;&gt;“virtually useless”&lt;/a&gt; because many urban areas are designed to be car-free, and consequently do not have ‘street segments’ in the same sense that other countries do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for us, the UK does not have the foresight to have many car-free urban areas. However, it does contain cities with highly variable histories of urban development. It seems / seemed implausible to me that the physical characteristics of street segments in, say, Milton Keynes, a purpose-built town which did not exist until the 1960s, were comparable to those in Edinburgh, which gained city status around 400 years ago, or Birmingham, which underwent dramatic urban regeneration following extensive bombing in World War II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To satisfy my own curiosity, and to gauge people’s interest / enthusiasm for the topic, I have spent a bit of time exploring the physical characteristics (length and sinuosity) of street segments in the UK. All the code used to generate these (very preliminary) findings is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/micro_units&#34;&gt;openly available&lt;/a&gt;. This work represents early thoughts and explorations, so if anyone has any comments or pointers, please do get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;street-segments&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Street segments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Street segments are defined as &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/j.1745-9125.2004.tb00521.x?casa_token=LSNEumu1MGwAAAAA:yco0oZEmw4BlaPq3coC4NKeywwXGv9zcLUaw4vf57spPyVA8qYzlCfxwYgSCm6fUGLkkldJ3Lly7rZU&#34;&gt;“the two block faces on both sides of the street between two intersections”&lt;/a&gt;. While the definition is geared towards the grid-based street networks of North America, we can apply a comparable concept to the UK using data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/business-government/products/open-map-roads&#34;&gt;Ordnance Survey Open Roads&lt;/a&gt;. Here, individual streets are defined (and given a unique ID) based on meeting intersections. As an example, the following visual plots street segments within a 500-metre buffer in the centre of Manchester. Each road ID has been coloured to help demonstrate the individual street segments (although note that there are a limited number of colours available).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/manc_ex.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the Ordnance Survey data fits the definition of street segments rather well. Each coloured line (i.e. individual ID) represents both sides of the street, and each line is segmented based on its intersection with another road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I collated this data for eight major towns and cities in the UK. Roads were clipped according to the town or city boundary (defined using the Open Street Map API – &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/micro_units&#34;&gt;see code&lt;/a&gt;), and those roads classified as motorways (highways) were removed. As evidenced below, the city boundaries sometimes include satellite towns and hamlets. This raises a related discussion about the universality of street segments in terms of urban/rural areas and how city boundaries are defined – I might return to this another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/study_regions_lq.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I focus on describing the physical characteristics of these street segments in two ways: &lt;strong&gt;length&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sinuosity&lt;/strong&gt;. By examining the degree to which street segments are homogeneous in length and sinuosity, both within and between study regions, we might shed some light on the degree to which they can be considered uniform, and in turn, ‘universal’ units of analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Length&lt;/strong&gt; is fairly self-explanatory. We are talking about it in the conventional sense (metric length) rather than other definitions (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10940-014-9235-4&#34;&gt;topological length&lt;/a&gt;). Although there is not much information out there, there appears to be at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; variation in the length of street segments used in crime concentration research. It is often added as a control variable, since longer streets might have more crime by virtue of their length, rather than whatever we are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But would excessive ranges (maximum - minimum) and variation in street segment length undermine the idea that street segments are a universally useful micro unit of analysis? Can we confidently compare study regions which are comprised of street segments with drastically different length characteristics (e.g. mean, variation, minimum, maximum)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sinuosity&lt;/strong&gt; is a fairly new concept to me. In crude terms, and at the risk of annoying geographers and mathematicians, sinuosity in this context represents a measure of ‘straightness’. It is calculated by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinuosity&#34;&gt;dividing the actual length of a line by the straight line distance&lt;/a&gt; (i.e. the distance between the start and end point). So, a perfectly straight street segment, for which the actual length and straight line length are the same, will have a sinuosity of 1, the smallest value possible. The example below, using street segments randomly sampled from Birmingham, demonstrates this concept. The black line represents the raw street segment, and the red line is the shortest distance from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/sin_example.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the reasoning behind examining sinuosity is to scrutinise the universality of street segments as meaningful behavioural spaces to study crime. A huge amount of variation in the sinuosity of street segments (either within the same study region, or between different study regions) might give reason to question this. Modern, grid-based cities might be almost entirely comprised of street segments with a sinuosity of 1. Cities with a long and convoluted history of urban development might have far more irregularity or quirks (e.g. right figure above). In which case, would the definition of ‘street segment’ generate units of analysis which still hold the same theoretical meaning?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;characteristics&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Characteristics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I have generated a series of descriptive statistics to try and summarise the length and sinuosity of the eight study regions. On top of statistics on raw length (e.g. ‘Mean length’) and sinuosity (e.g. ‘Mean sin.’) for each study region, I have calculated the proportion of street segments which are straight (‘Prop. straight’). This is simply the proportion of streets with a sinuosity of 1 (when rounded to six decimal places).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figures on &lt;strong&gt;length&lt;/strong&gt; alone generate some interesting discussion. The maximum lengths, which range from around 1200 metres to nearly 3600 metres, are clearly dragging the mean up. Recall that we removed motorways, but not A-roads or B-roads, which can be quite long. That said, A and B-roads are common even in dense urban areas, and contain plenty of opportunities for crime (e.g. petrol stations, residential dwellings). Removing them would come at a cost. The median might prove more useful. Quite a few study regions have a median street segment length of ~60 metres, but for instance, Edinburgh is noticeably longer (~72 metres) and Manchester a little shorter (~53 metres).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minimum values are amusingly small – perhaps showcasing some quirk in how the Ordnance Survey generate segments (e.g. roundabouts, which in &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10940-014-9235-4&#34;&gt;previous research&lt;/a&gt; required additional data handling).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;6%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;11%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;12%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;10%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;11%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;11%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;5%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;6%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;4%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;5%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;5%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;8%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;City&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Mean length (metres)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Median length (metres)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;SD length (metres)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Min. length (metres)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Max. length (metres)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Mean sin.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Median sin.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;SD sin.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Min. sin.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Max. sin.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Prop. straight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Birmingham&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;91.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;69.28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;83.48&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.01&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;3573.64&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.05&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;26.13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Leeds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;90.32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;62.62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;111.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.01&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;2716.05&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.05&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;30.39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;M. Keynes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;96.94&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;61.80&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;137.50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.03&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;3489.49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.81&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;219.30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.48&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Edinburgh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;102.59&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;72.44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;126.60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;3116.51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;16.53&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Manchester&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;68.02&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;53.40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;59.50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.02&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1227.02&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;4.04&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;632.77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.74&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Liverpool&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;81.10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;60.42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;72.65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.03&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1557.76&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.05&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;28.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.68&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Newcastle&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;85.51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;61.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;95.72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;3010.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;29.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.64&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;York&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;111.76&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;69.35&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;159.06&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;3442.73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1.06&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;8.66&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.58&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do these UK cities compare to elsewhere? &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10940-015-9276-3&#34;&gt;One study&lt;/a&gt; from The Hague (the Netherlands) reported a mean length of 94 metres and a standard deviation of 108 metres. This makes it fairly similar to Leeds, for instance. &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10940-009-9082-x?mod=article_inline&#34;&gt;A study in Boston&lt;/a&gt; (United States) reported a mean of 130 metres, although no standard deviation was mentioned. The minimum length in that study was ~3 metres, and maximum ~640 metres. &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10940-016-9304-y&#34;&gt;Another in Brooklyn Park&lt;/a&gt; (United States) had a mean length of 182 metres. This is considerably different to say, Manchester (Mean = 68 metres, Median = 53 metres), and strikes me as quite important when it comes to treating street segments as a universal micro unit of analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about &lt;strong&gt;sinuosity&lt;/strong&gt;? Generally speaking, it appears that street segments are fairly straight. The median sinuosity across all study regions is 1. Mean sinuosity is fairly low (but similar to the left example above – which isn’t exactly straight), although this may be dragged up by outliers, such as in Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proportion of street segments which are straight (sinuosity = 1, to nearest six decimal places) is quite high, but varies quite considerably between cities. In Milton Keynes, only 48% of street segments are straight, whereas this figure is 74% in Manchester. If you had asked me beforehand, I would have guessed that Milton Keynes would have had the highest percentage out of all the study regions, due to its unusual (for the UK) grid system. The surprise might result from the study region boundaries, which for Milton Keynes included villages and hamlets outside of the main town centre. Note that it still has a median sinuosity of 1 due to rounding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a very preliminary investigation into the homogeneity of street segments in terms of &lt;strong&gt;length&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sinuosity&lt;/strong&gt;. The idea is / was that street segments should have &lt;em&gt;reasonably&lt;/em&gt; homogeneous physical characteristics if we want to consider them to be ‘universal’ micro-level units of analysis in crime concentration research, and represent comparable behavioural spaces to study crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, findings certainly suggest that it is worth investigating this topic further. The length of street segments appears to vary quite considerably between study regions – both those presented here, and those in existing research. These differences may well narrow with further data handling, for instance, the removal of outliers or specific features such as a roundabouts. However, in that case, we might consider (1) outlining how and why street segments were kept/removed from analysis in a manner which is systematic and transparent, (2) demonstrating or discussing the implications of keeping/removing street segments, and/or (3) refining the definition of street segment to exclude those roads which are far too short or long to be reasonably comparable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of sinuosity, I have been surprised to see that many street segments in these UK study regions are more or less straight. However, the degree to which this holds true varies between study regions. Outliers with exceptionally high sinuosity might prove problematic in terms of keeping micro units of analysis uniform and comparable. In which case, the same three points above would apply regarding transparency, implications and definitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next steps might be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform some further data handling on the Ordnance Survey data to establish whether some systematic rules can create study regions with uniform street segments in terms of length and sinuosity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore the implications of the above for crime analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore alternative definitions of street segments (e.g. segment roads based on angle change between nodes, rather than intersections alone).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examine other physical characteristics (e.g. width).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International comparisons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;further-reading&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buil-Gil, D., Moretti, A., &amp;amp; Langton, S. (2020). The integrity of crime statistics: Assessing the impact of police data bias on crime mapping. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/myfhp&#34;&gt;Pre-print&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steenbeek, W., &amp;amp; Weisburd, D. (2016). Where the action is in crime? An examination of variability of crime across different spatial units in The Hague, 2001–2009. Journal of Quantitative Criminology, 32(3), 449-469.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor, R. B. (2015). Community criminology: Fundamentals of spatial and temporal scaling, ecological indicators, and selectivity bias (Vol. 12). NYU Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weisburd, D., Groff, E. R., &amp;amp; Yang, S. M. (2012). The criminology of place: Street segments and our understanding of the crime problem. Oxford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Akmedoids R package for generating directionally-homogeneous clusters of longitudinal data sets</title>
      <link>/publication/akmedoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/akmedoid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Data for Crime and Place Research. A Practical Guide in R</title>
      <link>/publication/osm_chapter/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/osm_chapter/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Six months in. Pandemic crime trends in England and Wales to August 2020</title>
      <link>/publication/covid_policinginsight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/covid_policinginsight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An examination of variability in offender residences across different spatial scales. A case study in Birmingham</title>
      <link>/publication/spatialscale_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/spatialscale_preprint/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crime and Anti-social Behaviour in Greater London</title>
      <link>/publication/covid_leeds1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/covid_leeds1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update: lockdown crime trends</title>
      <link>/post/update_lockdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/update_lockdown/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=4.9&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few weeks I have spent a bit of time exploring police recorded crime trends before and after the UK-wide lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been talk of lockdowns representing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12103-020-09546-0&#34;&gt;largest criminological experiment in history&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, determining the impact of this ‘experiment’ using police recorded crime data is not straightforward. Lots of parameters will have changed beyond people’s routine activities, amongst them, people’s ability and willingness to report crimes to the police, and policing resource allocation. It might be some time before we can fully understand how lockdowns have curbed the spatial and temporal patterns of crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.police.uk/&#34;&gt;open&lt;/a&gt; police recorded crime data can offer insight into how criminal behaviour might have changed in the past few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;visualising-trends&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Visualising trends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/lockdown-crime-trends-why-antisocial-behaviour-is-up-140479&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; of mine explored how crime trends changed in March and April following the lockdown using London as a case study. It used a descriptive visualisation which was inspired by those used in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/a26fbf7e-48f8-11ea-aeb3-955839e06441&#34;&gt;the FT&lt;/a&gt; to track coronavirus deaths whilst accounting for seasonal changes in death rates. A key characteristic of long-term crime trends is seasonality. To disentangle fluctuations in crime, and try to pinpoint irregularity resulting from lockdown measures, we must account for typical monthly fluctuations. Even then, monthly data is &lt;a href=&#34;https://the-sra.org.uk/SRA/Blog/whyyoucantidentifychangesincrimebycomparingthismonthtolastmonth.aspx&#34;&gt;far from ideal&lt;/a&gt;, but you can’t have everything (especially when working from your living room).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have some updated data – up to and including May, when some lockdown rules were relaxed – which demonstrates the start of a turnaround in crime trends. The code to make this visual is now available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/crime_covid_visual&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/full_met.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dramatic declines in burglary, robbery, theft and shoplifting observed in March and April have begun to reverse, or at least stabilise. Bicycle theft has more or less returned to normal when compared with previous years. As lockdown restrictions have eased, opportunities for crime have begun to (re)emerge. Counts are still unusually low amongst many crime types, but we are certainly witnessing a turnaround.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that we can attribute most ASB incidents to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-52298016&#34;&gt;lockdown breaches&lt;/a&gt;, it is no surprise to see counts beginning to decline. It will be interesting to see where this goes in June and July. We might see a resurgence of ‘traditional’ ASB amidst a fall in incidents associated with lockdown breaches, which will complicate the picture somewhat. We will be able to disentangle this through the analysis of secure records which provide some context to incidents (e.g. text logs), but the continued closure of universities (and thus, many secure data facilities) might slow this down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;drug-activity&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Drug activity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most interesting talking points is around drugs. Initially, some reports suggested that drug use would &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/may/03/coronavirus-crisis-could-increase-users-drug-habits-report&#34;&gt;rise&lt;/a&gt; during lockdown, partly due to the resultant strains on mental health. Now, there are reports that usage, at least for party drugs like ecstasy and cocaine, has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/jun/29/fall-in-use-of-party-drugs-as-more-britons-turn-to-alcohol-in-lockdown&#34;&gt;declined&lt;/a&gt;. We might then have expected a fall in drug offences, which includes possession, consumption and/or supply. Instead, we’ve seen an unprecedented increase throughout April and May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is perfectly plausible that drug activity, such as those relating to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalcrimeagency.gov.uk/what-we-do/crime-threats/drug-trafficking/county-lines&#34;&gt;‘County Lines’&lt;/a&gt;, has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2020/apr/13/gangs-still-forcing-children-into-county-lines-drug-trafficking-police-covid-19-lockdown&#34;&gt;not changed much&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://shoc.rusi.org/informer/part-2-how-covid-19-affecting-county-lines&#34;&gt;declined&lt;/a&gt;, even amidst an increase in the number of offences being recorded by the police. Some forces reported an increase in arrests simply due to dealers &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-52344249&#34;&gt;sticking out&lt;/a&gt; on empty streets. This has been described as like &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/gmhales/status/1249962083631980549&#34;&gt;shooting fish in a barrel&lt;/a&gt; for police, and represents a good example of how trends in police recorded crime – however useful – should be interpreted carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The monthly release of open police crime data in the UK offers a useful on-the-fly opportunity to examine how the lockdown may have impacted on crime. I’ll be updating this visual periodically upon new data releases to see how things are changing. Please do &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.samlangton.info/#contact&#34;&gt;get in contact&lt;/a&gt; if you have any suggestions or comments so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;further-reads&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further reads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashby, M. (2020). Changes in police calls for service during the early months of the 2020 coronavirus pandemic. &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/h4mcu/&#34;&gt;Pre-print&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Campedelli, G. M., Aziani, A., &amp;amp; Favarin, S. (2020). Exploring the effect of 2019-nCoV containment policies on crime: The case of los angeles. &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/gcpq8/&#34;&gt;Pre-print&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gerell, M. (2020). Minor covid-19 association with crime in Sweden, a five week follow up. &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/w7gka/&#34;&gt;Pre-print&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Halford, E., Dixon, A., Farrell, G., Malleson, N., &amp;amp; Tilley, N. (2020). Crime and coronavirus: social distancing, lockdown, and the mobility elasticity of crime. Crime Science, 9(1), 1-12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stickle, B., &amp;amp; Felson, M. (2020). Crime Rates in a Pandemic: the Largest Criminological Experiment in History. American Journal of Criminal Justice, 1-12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QGIS</title>
      <link>/project/qgis-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/qgis-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-to-qgis&#34;&gt;Introduction to QGIS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developed and taught a 1-day introductory course at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cmi.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cathie Marsh Institute&lt;/a&gt; (University of Manchester). Material is available on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/qgis_intro&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shorter introductory course has been held online for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opendatamanchester.org.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Open Data Manchester&lt;/a&gt;, with an accompanying 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/417967553&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;. Material is avaiable on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/qgis_intro/tree/odm_qgis_intro&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R</title>
      <link>/project/r-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/r-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have taught a number of courses using R and RStudio, including the development of teaching material both on my own and with colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-visualisation-in-r-using-crime-data&#34;&gt;Data visualisation in R using crime data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-day workshop on data visualisation and mapping at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cmi.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cathie Marsh Institute&lt;/a&gt; (University of Manchester) in collaboration with the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Data Service&lt;/a&gt;. Material can be found on the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/news-and-events/eventsitem/?id=5552&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Data Service website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course was subsequently updated and re-ran online with the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Data Service&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.methods.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Methods@Manchester&lt;/a&gt;. All material is available on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/data_viz_R_workshop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;r-for-police-forces&#34;&gt;R for police forces&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-day workshop on data wrangling and visualisation for West Midlands Police Force. Please get in contact for material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;r-for-criminologists&#34;&gt;R for criminologists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-day workshop on data wrangling, visualisation and mapping hosted at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.esc-eurocrim.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;European Society of Criminology&lt;/a&gt; with colleagues from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.space-place-crime.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Space Place and Crime working group&lt;/a&gt;. Material is available on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/ESC2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rpubs.com/spaceplacecrime&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rpubs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-started-in-r---an-introduction-to-data-analysis-and-visualisation&#34;&gt;Getting Started in R - an introduction to data analysis and visualisation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4-day comprehensive introductory course at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.methods.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Methods@Manchester&lt;/a&gt; summer school, co-taught with colleagues. Material is available as a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rcatlord.github.io/GSinR/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cluster-analysis-in-r&#34;&gt;Cluster analysis in R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-day workshop introducing cluster analysis in R at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cmi.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cathie Marsh Institute&lt;/a&gt; (University of Manchester), co-taught with a colleage. Please get in contact for material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;r-for-social-scientists&#34;&gt;R for social scientists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a qualified instructor for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://carpentries.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Data and Software Carpentries&lt;/a&gt;, and supported colleagues in teaching the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://datacarpentry.org/r-socialsci/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;social science workshop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-beginners-guide-to-statistics-for-criminology-and-criminal-justice-using-r&#34;&gt;A Beginner’s Guide to Statistics for Criminology and Criminal Justice Using R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co-authored a textbook introducing R for criminology students. Currently in press with Springer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lockdown crime trends. What we know and what we don&#39;t</title>
      <link>/post/lockdown_conversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/lockdown_conversation/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Understanding what has happened to crime during lockdown is challenging. We are in uncharted territory and it’s proving hard to draw definitive conclusions from the latest police recorded crime data. But a few trends, like a spike in antisocial behaviour and an increase in drug offences, are beginning to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes in people’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gstatic.com/covid19/mobility/2020-05-29_GB_Mobility_Report_en-GB.pdf&#34;&gt;movements and activities&lt;/a&gt; can impact on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/coronavirus-how-crime-changes-during-a-lockdown-134948&#34;&gt;opportunities&lt;/a&gt; available to potential offenders and, in turn, the volume and types of crime being committed. As a case study, we can look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.police.uk/data/&#34;&gt;Greater London&lt;/a&gt; and consider crimes recorded by the Metropolitan Police Service before and after the nationwide lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this data, I have visualised how the Met recorded antisocial behaviour and different crime types on a month-by-month basis. Importantly, there is enough open data to compare trends across years. This is useful for studying crime because many offence types are seasonal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, bicycle theft tends to increase in spring (around when the lockdown began) so looking at 2020 in isolation would be uninformative, or even misleading. This mimics the approach taken when &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/a26fbf7e-48f8-11ea-aeb3-955839e06441&#34;&gt;visually tracking&lt;/a&gt; coronvirus fatalities due to the seasonality of death rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/met_grid_crimetypes_less_ticks.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crimes such as burglary, shoplifting, robbery and theft all experienced remarkably sudden declines during April in comparison to previous years. Although we cannot differentiate individual days and weeks, some of these declines were already evident in March.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This aligns with what many will have expected. With most people spending so much time at home, shopping limited to essentials, and movement restricted to necessary travel and exercise, the opportunities available to commit such offences were severely curtailed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;anti-social-behaviour&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Anti-social behaviour&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the starkest trends observed is antisocial behaviour. Even by the end of March, recorded incidences were unusually high. But between March and April, the number of cases skyrocketed by over 270%. An increase at this time of year is expected, but a rise of this magnitude is unprecedented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is plausible that the lockdown resulted in a genuine shift in “traditional” antisocial behaviour, such as nuisance noise from neighbours. But the National Police Chiefs’ Council has said that this increase can largely be attributed to people &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-52298016&#34;&gt;breaching lockdown guidelines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture is not so clear for criminal offences. There has not yet been any discernible impact on public order or the possession of weapons. Violence and sexual offences appear to have declined more steeply than usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, using these charts in isolation, it is difficult to definitively attribute these changes to the lockdown. Even during less remarkable times, police recorded crime patterns can be subject to &lt;a href=&#34;https://the-sra.org.uk/SRA/Blog/whyyoucantidentifychangesincrimebycomparingthismonthtolastmonth.aspx&#34;&gt;short-term blips&lt;/a&gt;. Indeed, visualising the long-term trend for violence and sexual offences demonstrates that similarly volatile changes have occurred before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/viole_lines_lessticks.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drug offences appear to have gone up in comparison to previous years. Addiction experts have speculated that the lockdown could result in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/may/03/coronavirus-crisis-could-increase-users-drug-habits-report&#34;&gt;increase in drug usage&lt;/a&gt; among recreational users. At the same time, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-52344249&#34;&gt;some police forces&lt;/a&gt; have suggested that the demand for drugs has remained the same, but that drug dealers now stick out on otherwise empty streets, increasing the number of arrests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, these changes may not necessarily reflect actual changes in criminal behaviour. The long-term picture, visualised below, demonstrates that April’s increase might also be part of a wider upward trend in Greater London. The rise in recent years might be partly attributable to action taken over &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-norfolk-52892907&#34;&gt;county lines&lt;/a&gt; drug networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/drugs_lines_lessticks.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;exercising-caution&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exercising caution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some have labelled the nationwide lockdown as an ideal natural experiment to study how a shift in the opportunities available to offenders might impact on crime. But of course, it is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcl.ac.uk/news/no-the-coronavirus-crisis-isnt-a-cool-natural-experiment&#34;&gt;not that simple&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous parameters have changed. Recording practices for lockdown breaches have had to be adapted overnight. The willingness and ability of people to report crimes to the police, particularly for domestic offences, will have changed in ways that cannot yet be quantified. Calls to a national &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/coronavirus-murders-media-narrative-about-domestic-abuse-during-lockdown-is-wrong-and-harmful-137011&#34;&gt;domestic abuse&lt;/a&gt; helpline have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-52433520&#34;&gt;increased&lt;/a&gt;, but open police records do not flag which violent and sexual offences, for instance, were domestic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Policing priorities have also had to be adjusted in response to vague government guidelines and there has been considerable &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.polfed.org/gmp/news/2019/gmp-federation-chairman-stu-berry-reacts-to-the-latest-government-announcements-on-covid-19/&#34;&gt;strain&lt;/a&gt; on officers as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way of overcoming shortcomings in police data is by using victimisation surveys such as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ons.gov.uk/surveys/informationforhouseholdsandindividuals/householdandindividualsurveys/crimesurveyforenglandandwales&#34;&gt;Crime Survey for England and Wales&lt;/a&gt; that can capture crimes not reported or identified by the police. This largely resolves issues around under-reporting and includes additional crime types such as cybercrime which might &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.policy.manchester.ac.uk/digital-futures/2020/03/profiting-from-pandemics-covid-19-changing-routines-and-cyber-crimes/&#34;&gt;have increased&lt;/a&gt; during the lockdown. However, the survey data is not month-by-month and will not be released for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, open data in the UK represents a unique opportunity to track police recorded crime – as long as it is used with a degree of caution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GIS and Geovisual Analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/gis_chapter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/gis_chapter/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Even the most beautiful maps can be misleading</title>
      <link>/post/maps_conversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/maps_conversation/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From reporting &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/election/2017/results&#34;&gt;election results&lt;/a&gt; to issuing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/weather/2643743&#34;&gt;weather forecasts&lt;/a&gt;, maps offer a powerful, accessible and visually appealing way to convey complex information. Yet even the most beautiful maps can introduce some degree of misrepresentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see how, consider the latest statistics on deprivation released by the UK government. The government ranked 32,844 neighbourhoods, based on measures of deprivation such as income, employment, health and crime. The figures were widely reported, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-49812519&#34;&gt;the BBC&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2019/sep/26/wealthy-incomers-changing-profile-of-londons-most-deprived-areas&#34;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-7507575/Essex-seaside-village-Jaywick-named-Englands-deprived-neighbourhood.html&#34;&gt;Daily Mail&lt;/a&gt;, reigniting long-standing debates about persistent inequality in England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, many outlets &lt;a href=&#34;https://imd2019.group.shef.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;used maps&lt;/a&gt; to share these findings with the public. But using traditional boundaries can divert readers’ attention away from important information. In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-49812519&#34;&gt;BBC’s&lt;/a&gt; map of deprivation across local authorities, for instance, sparsely populated rural areas dominate a disproportionately large area, while urban areas, such as London, containing millions of people, are rendered almost invisible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The map included in the BBC’s report on deprivation is interesting. It would be good to take a look at the Ofsted rating of schools in the most deprived areas... &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iUR2hINBRn&#34;&gt;https://t.co/iUR2hINBRn&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/lFq6s8l1In&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/lFq6s8l1In&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; SailingAway (@Heatherleatt) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Heatherleatt/status/1177466763312689152?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 27, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;distorted-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Distorted data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/t6agd/&#34;&gt;research shows&lt;/a&gt; that people can interpret information inaccurately, when they look at maps with these shortcomings. But other techniques can be used to create a more accurate impression of the underlying data. For instance, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1467-8306.2004.09401004.x?casa_token=PCQuJ1wUlkoAAAAA:m8aWeOyHWcKv-iL8T1-bXlcunBnzZV2lkAz3-gYAxUtgRCihbAYOIWz8-HJFvSOO8WP4W25tLA&#34;&gt;cartograms&lt;/a&gt; deliberately distort geography by scaling areas according to a specific variable, such as local population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.arcgis.com/home/item.html?id=b686a7679cb747e9825d1d1bb6b26046&#34;&gt;Dorling cartograms&lt;/a&gt; take this one step further, scaling areas according to a specified variable, but also representing each area using the same shape, such as a square or a circle. Other methods achieve uniformity in both size and shape: &lt;a href=&#34;http://gisruk.org/ProceedingsGISRUK2018/GISRUK2018_Contribution_023.pdf&#34;&gt;hexograms&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jbaileyh/geogrid&#34;&gt;geogrids&lt;/a&gt; transform the original boundaries of the map into hexagons or squares of the same size, while still aiming to preserve their original arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mapping neighbourhood deprivation in England represents &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/these-maps-show-how-tricky-it-is-to-measure-inequality-in-local-areas-across-england-109143&#34;&gt;a significant challenge&lt;/a&gt;, even for experts. This is because the government defines a neighbourhood as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ons.gov.uk/methodology/geography/ukgeographies/censusgeography&#34;&gt;“lower super output area”&lt;/a&gt; – each of which contains around 1,500 residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because highly deprived neighbourhoods tend to be densely populated, they are less visible on a regular map. By contrast, wealthier suburban areas – which are often less densely populated and therefore much larger – dominate the map. So there’s a risk that readers might draw inaccurate conclusions about the level of deprivation in any given area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;shaping-up&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shaping up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.arcgis.com/home/item.html?id=b686a7679cb747e9825d1d1bb6b26046&#34;&gt;Dorling cartograms&lt;/a&gt; scaled by resident population, and regular hexagonal &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jbaileyh/geogrid&#34;&gt;geogrids&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve attempted to minimise any misrepresentation. Take the example of Blackpool, which was &lt;a href=&#34;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/835115/IoD2019_Statistical_Release.pdf&#34;&gt;ranked&lt;/a&gt; the most deprived local authority in England. Around 42% of neighbourhoods in Blackpool are in the top 10% most deprived in England (the “first decile”). Yet these neighbourhoods only make up around 29% of the city’s actual area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/blackpool.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a Dorling cartogram scaled by resident population size, neighbourhoods in the first decile now take up 41% of the map’s area, and the larger, less deprived neighbourhoods (in light blue) have been shrunk accordingly to become less dominant. With a regular hexagonal geogrid, the map now mimics the underlying data, with neighbourhoods in the first decile of deprivation taking up 42% of the total area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variation in the shapes and sizes of Blackpool’s neighbourhoods can no longer divert attention or mislead readers, and arguably, the underlying data has been conveyed more accurately than with the original map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mapping-deprivation-differently&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mapping deprivation differently&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A striking difference can be seen using different types of maps to visualise deprivation in Burnley and Hartlepool, which were among England’s most deprived local authorities. Both areas are characterised by many small, densely populated neighbourhoods in the first decile (most deprived), surrounded by much larger and wealthier suburbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/burn_hart.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, deprivation appears understated in the map that uses the original boundaries. But with the Dorling cartogram (again scaled by population) and the hexagonal geogrids, the issue can be somewhat rectified. This comes with its own difficulties, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geogrid in particular pushed some neighbourhoods further apart and forced some closer together than they appear on the original map. This might prove problematic in cases where the primary aim of the map is to convey distinct geographic patterns, such as the clustering of highly deprived neighbourhoods. In making the transformation, these patterns might be lost, or spurious patterns generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;encouraging-experimentation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Encouraging experimentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Birmingham and Manchester – ranked in the top ten most deprived local authorities – present a different challenge. With much larger populations, and many more neighbourhoods to visualise, the original map presents an overwhelming amount of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/birm_manc.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, both the Dorling cartogram and the geogrid perform admirably, scaling down the visual impact of larger, wealthier areas (especially in the north of Birmingham) and making the maps easier to read – without skewing the geographic patterning of deprivation across each city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no firm rules about how best to create beautiful but accurate maps. In this case, using the latest neighbourhood deprivation data in England, mapping out the original boundaries can clearly introduce some degree of misrepresentation. There’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/t6agd/&#34;&gt;real value&lt;/a&gt; in experimenting with different cartographic techniques – and media organisations and the government would do well to think outside the box when it comes to sharing the latest findings with the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cartograms, hexograms and regular grids. Minimising misrepresentation in spatial data visualisations</title>
      <link>/publication/hexo_epb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/hexo_epb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When crime drops, the demands on the police don’t necessarily fall</title>
      <link>/post/crimedrop_conversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/crimedrop_conversation/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On a day-to-day basis, the exposure citizens have to the police is often fleeting, with officers passing by in a blur as they respond to emergency calls. Official crime figures can be disputed, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/445662/rec-crime-2003-2015.ods&#34;&gt;the long-term trend&lt;/a&gt; appears to be that levels of crime in England and Wales are heading downward. Yet it is a myth to think that an apparent drop in crime relieves some of the pressures placed on police forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, the demands placed on police forces do not originate primarily from obvious criminal behaviour. Forces are increasingly burdened with what’s called “latent” crime demand, such as child sexual exploitation or modern slavery, where victims are afraid or unwilling to approach police, as well as non-crime issues, such as missing persons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The volume of this demand, and the time spent on addressing it, is much more problematic to estimate, and yet the safety of the public depends on both the police and the government having a handle on such estimations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out on the streets, police forces need to demonstrate an understanding of current and future demand to allocate resources efficiently and ensure calls are responded to in time. In Westminster, the funding allocations to the 43 forces of England and Wales are dictated by estimations of demand. In an era of austerity, measuring this demand has never been more crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;measuring-demand&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Measuring demand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reports by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.college.police.uk/News/College-news/Documents/Demand%20Report%2023_1_15_noBleed.pdf&#34;&gt;College of Policing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.justiceinspectorates.gov.uk/hmic/wp-content/uploads/state-of-policing-2016.pdf&#34;&gt;HM Inspectorate of Constabulary&lt;/a&gt; (HMIC), have shown how the realities of modern policing render traditional estimates of demand outdated and inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its annual review of policing in England and Wales, HMIC rates how well each police force estimates the current and future demand for their services. For their latest report, published in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.justiceinspectorates.gov.uk/hmic/wp-content/uploads/state-of-policing-2016.pdf&#34;&gt;March 2017&lt;/a&gt; and covering inspections between February 2016 and March 2017, the message is clear: most forces are doing a good job, but there is room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The map below, generated using open-source &lt;a href=&#34;http://geoportal.statistics.gov.uk/datasets/3e5a096a8c7c456fb6d3164a3f44b005_0&#34;&gt;spatial data&lt;/a&gt;, plots the latest force ratings. It paints a positive picture for England and Wales, but nine out of 43 police forces require improvement, and only a handful managed to achieve the top grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/map_police1.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key component of improving police awareness of their demand will be refining the understanding of “latent” and non-crime demand. Latent demand often involves vulnerable people who are unwilling to come forward due to the nature of the crime, or live in communities with a widespread distrust of the police. It is therefore extremely difficult to make reliable estimations about this kind of demand on police time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A substantial proportion of the demands placed on police forces originate from non-crime issues such as mental health. Although &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201516/cmselect/cmhaff/476/47608.htm&#34;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; vary, some forces estimate that 70% to 80% of their demand is comprised of non-crime incidents. A number of forces &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201516/cmselect/cmhaff/476/47608.htm&#34;&gt;believe&lt;/a&gt; that the increase in non-criminal incidents being dealt with by the police may be partially driven by cuts to other areas of the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;money-depends-on-it&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Money depends on it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure that police forces are allocated money appropriately, in the interests of public safety and economic efficiency, the government also needs to demonstrate an understanding of demand. The issue of police funding remains a highly charged one, and budget cuts were &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/fact-check-have-the-conservatives-protected-police-and-counter-terrorism-budgets-78782&#34;&gt;keenly debated&lt;/a&gt; during the 2017 election campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The map here uses recent police funding &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/588196/Police_Grant_report_2017-18_Accessible.pdf&#34;&gt;figures&lt;/a&gt; from 2017-2018 to demonstrate the vast sums of public money involved, and how much these sums can vary between police force areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/map_police2.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the implications and public concern over police funding, refining the formula used to apportion money has been fraught with difficulties. A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201516/cmselect/cmhaff/476/476.pdf&#34;&gt;December 2015 report&lt;/a&gt; by MPs on the Home Affairs Committee demonstrated the problems the government has faced when attempting to estimate demand for the purposes of funding allocations. It detailed how a freshly proposed police funding formula, which aimed to simplify the estimation process, was almost immediately put on hold following the realisation that incorrect data was being used for the calculation. Although &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201617/cmselect/cmhaff/1093/1093.pdf&#34;&gt;a new government consultation&lt;/a&gt; on a revised funding calculation was launched in September 2016, its outcome has not yet been announced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-role-of-experts&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The role of experts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic researchers are often &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2015/04/09/academic-promotion-scholars-popular-media/&#34;&gt;justifiably scolded&lt;/a&gt; for not engaging with real-world discussions, and failing to offer practical solutions to contemporary problems in society. Yet here they clearly have something to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HMIC &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.justiceinspectorates.gov.uk/hmic/wp-content/uploads/state-of-policing-2016.pdf&#34;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that some police forces have made significant improvements to their demand estimations by working with academic research institutions who can provide much needed methodological expertise. But such collaborations are not widespread. Only recently has there been an acceptance that a concerted collaborative effort, including academic experts, is required to improve the government’s demand-based funding formula. Hopefully in this way past errors by the Home Office can be rectified, and trust in the system restored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent history tells us that collaborations can be fruitful, and that there is the potential to drastically improve estimations of demand through such partnership. Academics, police forces and the government must bear the responsibility of instigating further change. The safety of the public may depend on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Residential burglary target selection. An analysis at the property-level using Google Street View</title>
      <link>/publication/burg_ag/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/burg_ag/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper summary: police demand and persons with mental ill-health</title>
      <link>/post/pmih_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pmih_paper/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a common misconception that police spend most of their time responding with ‘blues and twos’ to crime reports. A extraordinary amount of demand for police services has little or nothing to do with crime. A recent study from Philadelphia demonstrated that of the 1.07 million calls for police service made during 2019, only 40% actually related to crime. The rest related to quality of life (e.g. loud music), community (e.g. missing persons) and medical/public health incidents (e.g. checks on well-being), amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since my article in The Conversation, I have become increasingly intrigued by the complexities of understanding and measuring police demand. This has largely driven by some of the amazing research that has been published in recent years (see readings below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many countries, one such demand type is particularly concerning; those originating from incidents involving people with mental ill-health. In England and Wales, forces have reported that around 2% of incidents relate to mental health, but this is widely understood to be an &lt;strong&gt;underestimate&lt;/strong&gt; due to inconsistencies in how incidents are flagged. Not only this, but the proportion of emergency calls for service does not necessarily reflect the &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt; police actually consume dealing with such incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two issues represented a key motivation for the study. We sought to (1) provide an improved, data-driven estimate of the proportion of calls for service involving mental ill-healh, and (2) estimate the amount of time officers spend resolving such incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
