<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ggplot2 | Samuel Langton</title>
    <link>/tag/ggplot2/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/ggplot2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>ggplot2</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu347c2c227070d4d829f6f2e71f22c263_2514_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>ggplot2</title>
      <link>/tag/ggplot2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update: visualising lockdown crime trends</title>
      <link>/post/update_lockdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/update_lockdown/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Over the past few weeks I have spent a bit of time exploring police recorded crime trends before and after the UK-wide lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been talk of lockdowns representing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12103-020-09546-0&#34;&gt;largest natural experiment in criminological history&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, determining the impact of this ‘experiment’ when demonstrations involve police recorded crime data is not straightforward. Lots of parameters will have changed beyond people’s routine activities, amongst them, people’s ability and willingness to report crimes to the police, and policing resource allocation. It might be some time before we can fully understand how lockdowns have curbed the spatial and temporal patterns of crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.police.uk/&#34;&gt;open&lt;/a&gt; police recorded crime data can offer a unique insight into how criminal behaviour &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; have changed in the past few months. A recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/lockdown-crime-trends-why-antisocial-behaviour-is-up-140479&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; of mine explored crime trends in London using a visualisation inspired by those used in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/a26fbf7e-48f8-11ea-aeb3-955839e06441&#34;&gt;the FT&lt;/a&gt; to track coronavirus deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visual was entirely descriptive, but showed some preliminary insight. As expected, many crime types such as burglary and and shoplifting fell considerably, whereas drug offences and anti-social behaviour (ASB) increased. Of course, part of the point of the article was to highlight the difficulties interpreting these trends. For instance, the dramatic rise in ASB is likely to reflect &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/amp/uk-52298016&#34;&gt;lockdown breaches&lt;/a&gt; rather than a genuine shift in ‘traditional’ forms of ASB (e.g. nuisance noise).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have some updated data – upto and including May – which demonstrate the start of a turnaround. The code to make this visual is now available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/langtonhugh/crime_covid_visual&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/full_met.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
