<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>text mining | Samuel Langton</title>
    <link>/tag/text-mining/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/text-mining/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>text mining</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu347c2c227070d4d829f6f2e71f22c263_2514_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>text mining</title>
      <link>/tag/text-mining/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policing and mental ill-health. Using big data to assess the scale and severity of, and the frontline resources committed to, mental ill-health related calls-for-service</title>
      <link>/publication/pmih_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/pmih_preprint/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper summary: police demand and persons with mental ill-health</title>
      <link>/post/pmih_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pmih_paper/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a common misconception that police spend most of their time responding with ‘blues and twos’ to crime reports. A extraordinary amount of demand for police services has little or nothing to do with crime. A recent study from Philadelphia demonstrated that of the 1.07 million calls for police service made during 2019, only 40% actually related to crime. The rest related to quality of life (e.g. loud music), community (e.g. missing persons) and medical/public health incidents (e.g. checks on well-being), amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since my article in The Conversation, I have become increasingly intrigued by the complexities of understanding and measuring police demand. This has largely driven by some of the amazing research that has been published in recent years (see readings below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many countries, one such demand type is particularly concerning; those originating from incidents involving people with mental ill-health. In England and Wales, forces have reported that around 2% of incidents relate to mental health, but this is widely understood to be an &lt;strong&gt;underestimate&lt;/strong&gt; due to inconsistencies in how incidents are flagged. Not only this, but the proportion of emergency calls for service does not necessarily reflect the &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt; police actually consume dealing with such incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two issues represented a key motivation for the study. We sought to (1) provide an improved, data-driven estimate of the proportion of calls for service involving mental ill-healh, and (2) estimate the amount of time officers spend resolving such incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
